Guide to the Karen Halverson Photographs of the American West
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Dakota Survey, 2011; Series IV; 0.17; (1 box)
  Arranged by the creator.
  Dakota Survey, 2011, depicts views of sites in North Dakota and South Dakota with an emphasis on lines and grids in the landscape. Identified locations in North Dakota include Dickinson, Edmore, Garrison, Grace City, Grafton, Max, Rugby, Sentinel Butte, and Williston. Identified locations in South Dakota include Bowdle, Flasher, Kadoka, Leola, Newell, Onida, and Scenic. The photographs show agricultural fields, road intersections, and structures, including an abandoned drive-in, fences, and windmills. A journal by Halverson accompanies the photographs with contents that span July 11 to August 5, 2011, and describes sites and her compositing of the images.
  The images are printed as color inkjet prints on Canson Platine Fibre Rag Paper, 20 x 24 inches (51 x 61 centimeters). The prints are titled with the location of the image. The collection comprises an edition numbered two of ten.
  In an artist's statement that accompanied the collection upon acquisition in 2016, Halverson describes the work:
  In the summer of 2011, without itinerary or preconception, I drove to the Dakotas. I knew that, by and large, Dakota vistas would be broad and flat, making for a straight horizon line. But, heading west from Grand Forks, I was interested to find how strongly I experienced the land as a grid. Roads run in straight lines, north / south or east / west. Property lines and rows of trees known as shelterbelts do the same. This arrangement reflects the Homestead Act, signed into law by President Lincoln in 1862. Making use of geographical surveys, the law granted sections of land to settlers pledged to "improve" them. Euro-Americans were displacing Native Americans. Cultivated crops would replace native prairie grasses.
  I had seen the grid from the air, but had not before experienced the geometry of the Plains on the ground. I chose the square photographic format, as an expression of the geometry I saw before me. The landscape presented a pattern, based on flat terrain and especially on land use. I see the Dakota Survey images as landscape sections, emphasizing the lines and forms that nature and human history have created.
  - Journal, 2011 (Box 31, Folder 181)
  - Scenic, South Dakota, 2011 (Box 31, Folder 182)
  - Dickinson, North Dakota, 2011 (Box 31, Folder 183)
  - Dickinson, North Dakota, 2011 (Box 31, Folder 184)
  - Edmore, North Dakota, 2011 (Box 31, Folder 185)
  - Grafton, North Dakota, 2011 (Box 31, Folder 186)
  - Kadoka, South Dakota, 2011 (Box 31, Folder 187)
  - Rugby, North Dakota, 2011 (Box 31, Folder 188)
  - Grace City, North Dakota, 2011 (Box 31, Folder 189)
  - Sentinel Butte, North Dakota, 2011 (Box 31, Folder 190)
  - Williston, North Dakota, 2011 (Box 31, Folder 191)
  - Leola, South Dakota, 2011 (Box 31, Folder 192)
  - Onida, South Dakota, 2011 (Box 31, Folder 193)
  - Leola, South Dakota, 2011 (Box 31, Folder 194)
  - Newell, South Dakota, 2011 (Box 31, Folder 195)
  - Garrison, North Dakota, 2011 (Box 31, Folder 196)
  - Flasher, South Dakota, 2011 (Box 31, Folder 197)
  - Near Devils Lake, North Dakota, 2011 (Box 31, Folder 198)
  - Bowdle, South Dakota, 2011 (Box 31, Folder 199)
  - Max, North Dakota, 2011 (Box 31, Folder 200)
  - Grafton, North Dakota, 2011 (Box 31, Folder 201)